<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt" ?>
<!-- generated by https://github.com/cabo/kramdown-rfc2629 version 1.0.30 -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc strict="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc text-list-symbols="-o*+"?>
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-wissingh-icnrg-terminology-01">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="ICN Terminology">Community Information-Centric Networking (CICN): Terminology</title>

    <author fullname="Alex Afanasyev" initials="A." surname="Afanasyev">
      <organization>UCLA</organization>

      <address>
        <email>aa@cs.ucla.edu</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="David Oran" initials="D." surname="Oran">
      <organization>Network Systems Research &amp; Design</organization>

      <address>
        <email>daveoran@orandom.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Christian Tschudin" initials="C." surname="Tschudin">
      <organization>University of Basel</organization>

      <address>
        <email>christian.tschudin@unibas.ch</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Bastiaan Wissingh" initials="B.F." surname="Wissingh">
      <organization>TNO</organization>

      <address>
        <email>bastiaan.wissingh@tno.nl</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Christopher A. Wood" initials="C." surname="Wood">
      <organization>University of California Irvine</organization>

      <address>
        <email>woodc1@uci.edu</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Lixia Zhang" initials="L." surname="Zhang">
      <organization>UCLA</organization>

      <address>
        <email>lixia@cs.ucla.edu</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="February" year="2017"/>

    <area>General</area>

    <workgroup>icnrg</workgroup>

    <keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>Information Centric Networking (ICN) is a new paradigm where
      network communications are accomplished by requesting named content,
      instead of sending packets to destination addresses. The Community
      ICN (CICN) project represents the harmonization of the NDN and
      CCNx projects. This document provides an overview of the terminology and
      definitions that have been used in describing concepts in these two projects.
      While there are other ICN architectures, they are not part of the CICN
      vision and as such are out of scope for this document.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction">
      <t>Information-centric networking (ICN) is an approach to evolve the
        Internet infrastructure from the existing host-centric design to
        a data-centric architecture where accessing data by name becomes the essential
        network primitive. The goal is to let applications refer to data independently of their location or means of
        transportation, which --for immutable data items-- enables native multicast delivery, ubiquitous
        in-network caching and replication of data objects.</t>

      <t>As the work on this topic continues to evolve, many new terms are
        emerge over time. The goal of this document is to provide a thorough
        collection of these terms with a corresponding definition as they are
        used in the CCNx, NDN, and, ultimately, the joint Community ICN (CICN)
        projects. Other, historic ICN projects like NetInf, XIA or Mobility First
        are not covered and will be the subject of other documents.</t>

      <t>To help provide the context of the individual terms to be defined, in this
        draft we first sketch the bigger picture of an ICN network, introducing
        the basic concepts and identifying the major components in the
        architecture in section 2 after which in section 3 ICN related terms
        are listed by different categories.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="architecture" title="A Sketch of the Big Picture of ICN">

      <t>In networking terms, an ICN is a delivery infrastructure for
      named data. For other, complementing views see
      <xref target="semantics-and-usage" />.
      The following list
      describes basic ICN concepts needed to discuss the
      implementation of this service abstraction:</t>

      <t>Packet (PDU) vs Frame:</t>
      <t>NDN and CCNx introduce Protocol Data Units (PDUs) which typically
      are larger than the maximum transmission unit of the underlying networking
      technology. We refer to PDUs as 'packets' and the segmented parts that
      traverse MTU-bound links as 'frames'.</t>

      <t>Request-Reply Protocol (Interest and Data Packet):</t>
        <t>An ICN's lookup service is implemented by defining two
        types of network packet formats: Interest packets that request
        content by name, and data packets that carry the requested
        content.  The returned data packet must match the request's
        parameters (e.g., having a partially or fully matching
        name). If the request is ambigious and several data packets
        would satisfy the request, the ICN network will typically
        return only one matching data packet.</t>

      <t>Packet and Content Names:</t>
        <t>Without an irrefutable binding between a
        name of a data packet and its content, data packet names
        would be useless for fetching specific content. In ICN,
        verification of a data packet's name-to-content binding is achieved
        through cryptographic means, either by (1) a
        cryptographic signature that explicitely binds an
        application-chosen name to a data packet's content, or (2) relying on an
        implicit name (cryptographic hash of the data packet) that the data
        consumer obtained through other means.</t>

      <t>Data Authenticity and Encryption:</t>
        <t>Any data consumers and network element can validate the authenticity of
            a data packet by verifying its cryptographic name-to-content binding.
            In contrast, whether a data packet's content (payload) itself
            is encrypted or not is irrelevant to the ICN network: The use
            and the management of content encryption keys is an application-layer
            concern.
        </t>

        <t>Trust:</t>
          <t>Data authenticity is distinct from data trustworthiness, though
              the two concepts are related. A packet is authentic if it has a valid
              name-to-content binding. A packet is trustworthy, i.e., it comes
              from a reputable or trusted origin, if this binding is only valid
              in the context of a trust model. For example, if a corresponding trust infrastructure
              (e.g., PKI) is in place, a packet's signature even enables to assess
              authenticity with relation to to real world identities which can be trusted
              or not.
          </t>

      <t>Segmenting and Versioning:</t>
        <t>An ICN network will be engineered for some packet size
        limit. As application-level data objects will often be
        considerably larger, objects must be segmented into multiple
        data packets. The names for these data packets can, for
        example, be constructed by choosing one application-level
        object name to which a different suffix is added for each
        segment. The same method can be used to handle different
        versions of an application-level object by including a version
        number into the name of the overall object. Handling
        link-layer technologies which lead to even smaller
        fragmentation of ICN packets is done inside the ICN network
        and is not visible at the service interface.
        </t>

      <t>ICN Node:</t>
      <t>A node within an ICN network can fulfill the role of a data producer, a data consumer,
        and/or a forwarder for interest and data packets. When a forwarder has connectivity
        to neighbor nodes, it performs interest and data packet forwarding in real time. It can
        also behave like a packet mule, that is it may carry an interest or data packet over
        some distance before forwarding it to next node. An ICN node may also run routing
        protocols to assist its interest forwarding decisions.</t>

        <!-- caw: I removed the forwarding plane here since it can be stateful or stateless -->
      <t>Forwarding Plane:</t>
      <t>The canonical way of implementing packet forwarding in an ICN network like NDN and CCNx
        relies on three data structures that capture a node's state: a Forwarding Interest
        Table (FIB), a Pending Interest Table (PIT), and a Content Store (CS). It also utilizes
        interest forwarding strategies which takes input from both FIB and measurements to make
        interest forwarding decisions.  When a node receives an ICN interest packet, it checks
        its CS and PIT to find a matching name; if no match is found, the node records the interest
        in its PIT and forwards the interest to the next hop(s) towards the requested content
        based on the information in its FIB. There exist alternative approaches which
        aim at reducing the amount of state that a nodes must keep, up to fully PIT-less designs
        using packets for keeping state but without changing the overall service model.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="categorized-terms" title="Terms by category">

      <section title="Generic terms">
        <t><list>
          <t>Information-Centric Networking (ICN): a networking architecture that retrieves data packets as response to interest packets.
             Content-Centric Networking (CCNx) and Named Data Networking (NDN) are two types of ICN architectures. Community ICN (CICN) is
             a Linux Foundation project that represents the harmonization of the NDN and CCNx projects.</t>

          <t>Data packet: a network-level packet that carries payload, uniquely identified by a name, and is directly secured.
              <list style="empty">
                  <t>Common aliases include: data, data object, content object packet, data message, named data object, named data.</t>
            </list>
          </t>

          <t>Interest packet: a network-level packet that expresses the request for a data
              packet using either an exact name or a name prefix. An interest packet may optionally carry a set of additional
              restrictions (e.g. interest selectors). An interest may  be associated with additional information to facilitate
              forwarding and can include interest lifetime, hop limit, forwarding hints, labels, etc.  In different ICN designs,
              the set of additional associated information may vary.
              <list style="empty">
              <t>Common aliases include: interest, interest message, information request</t>
            </list>
        </t>

          <!--<t>Location-independence (?)</t>[LZ: I’d suggest to move all location/identifier related stuff into one place, which is not here]-->

          <t>Data packet immutability: after a data packet is created, it cannot change. If the content carried in the data packet is mutable, versioning should be used, so that each version uniquely identifies an immutable instance of the content. This allows disambiguation of coordination in distributed systems.</t>
        </list></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="name-types" title="Terms related to Name Types">
        <t><list>
          <t>Name: a data packet identifier. An ICN name is expressive, flexible
              and can be application-specific (akin to a HTTP URL). A Name may encode information about application context, semantics,
              locations (topological, geographical, hyperbolic, etc.), a service name, etc. A Name is a sequence of non-empty name components (see below).
              The components of a name are said to be complete if they uniquely identify a single data packet. A Name is exact if its
              components are complete.
              <list style="empty">
              <t>Common aliases include: data name, interest name, content name.</t>
          </list>
          </t>

          <t>Name component: a sequence of octets and optionally a numeric type representing a single label in the hierarchical structured name.
              <list style="empty">
              <t>Common aliases include: name segment (as in CCNx).</t>
          </list>
          </t>

          <t>Packet ID: a unique cryptographic identifier for a data packet. Typically, this is the cryptographic hash digest of a data packet, including its name, payload, meta information, and signature.</t>

          <t>Full Name: An exact Name with the Packet ID of the corresponding data packet.</t>

          <t>Prefix Name: A Name with incomplete components.
              <list style="empty">
              <t>Common aliases include: prefix.</t>
          </list>
          </t>

          <t>Selector: Depending on the implementation, some restrictors show up as name components or as explicit fields of an interest. Selectors are not
              'names' in a proper sense although they are able to "name content." Examples include selectors used to reference nameless objects, specify publisher restriction, etc.
              In that sense, a single data packet will have multiple 'name-like properties' through which it can be referenced, interest packets are able to express them.
              <list style="empty">
              <t>Common aliases include: restrictor.</t>
            </list>
          </t>

           <!-- caw: this is misplaced a nonce has nothing to do with names -->
           <t>Nonce: ... transiently 'names' an interest instance</t>

          <!-- Naming scalability (?)  [LZ: probably a confusion with routing scalability] -->
        </list></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="name-usage" title="Terms related to Name Usage">
        <t><list>
          <t>Naming scheme (ICN naming scheme): a convention/agreement/specification for the data packet naming. Structures a name space.</t>

          <t>Hierarchically structured naming: the naming scheme that assigns and interprets name as a sequence of labels (name components)
              with hierarchical structure. A structure provides useful context information for the name.
              <list style="empty">
              <t>Common aliases include: hierarchical naming, structured naming.</t>
          </list>
            <!-- Name or parts of it can be “human-readable” to ease human interaction, but a hierarchical name is ultimately a sequence of ICN node interpretable name components. -->
          </t>

          <t>Flat naming: the naming scheme that assigns and interprets name as a single label (name component) without any internal structure. This can be considered a special (or degenerated) case of structured names. </t>

          <!-- <t>Information Identifiers (?):</t> <t>Location prefix (?):</t> [LZ: I commented these out, to minimize confusions-->

          <t>Segmentation: a process of splitting large application content into a set of uniquely named data packets.
              When using hierarchically structured name, each created data packet has a common prefix and additional
              component representing the segment (chunk) number.
              <list style="empty">
              <t>Common aliases include: chunking (as in CCNx).</t>
          </list>
          </t>

          <t>Versioning: a process of assigning a unique name to the revision of the content carried in the data packet.
              When using a hierarchically structured name, the version of the data packet can be carried in a dedicated name
              component (e.g., prefix identifies data, unique version component identifies the revision of the data).
          </t>
          <!-- What would be the difference when putting the version before the segment number? Is
          one then versioning individual segments instead of application layer content? -->

          <t>Fragmentation: a process of splitting data packets into frames so that they can be
              transmitted over the link with a smaller MTU size.</t>
        </list></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="security" title="Terms related to Data-Centric Security">
        <t><list>
          <t>Directly secured data packet: a data packet with inherent security properties (authenticity and optionally
              confidentiality), i.e., the security properties stay with the data packet regardless where it is
              stored and how it is retrieved.</t>

          <t>Data authenticator: a set of parameters carried in the data packet that is used to verify integrity and authenticity of the data packet.
              The Data authenticator can include a cryptographic signature (RSA, ECDSA, HMAC, etc.),
              meta information about the signature (e.g., validity period), and additional information to facilitate signature verification
              (e.g., key locator, key ID, HMAC tag identifier, etc.)
              <list style="empty">
              <t>Common aliases include: content authenticator.</t>
            </list>
          </t>

          <t>Data confidentiality credentials: a set of parameters carried in the data packet that is used to identify how the confidential data
              can be decrypted by authorized consumers.</t>

          <t>Key owner (same as Identity): an entity (user, device, program, program instance, module in the program instance, etc.) that
              owns private key(s) and the corresponding public key(s).</t>

          <t>Certificate: a data packet that carries a public key as payload with optional additional meta information regarding the key (e.g., validity period, signature time, etc.).
              Ownership of the public key is made implicitly through the name of the packet or explicitly through meta information.</t>
              <!-- The key belongs to the key owner and can be associated with it implicitly through the name or explicitly through meta information.</t> -->

          <t>Key locator: Parameter(s) that identify the ICN key, which can be the ICN key name, ICN key prefix, ICN key ID, etc.</t>

          <t>Key ID: Unique identifier (e.g., hash digest) for a public or secret key.</t>

          <t>Trust model: a model or framework that defines trust relationships, i.e., which entity (represented by an ICN
              key) is authorized to sign which data packets.</t>

          <t>Trust schema: a formal description of a trust model, e.g., in the form of a set of name-based relationships between
              data and key names and a set of the trust anchors.</t>

          <t>Trust anchor: an ICN key that is assumed to be trusted within the context of a specific trust model.</t>

          <t>ICN key chain: a chain of ICN keys (certificates) wherein each key (certificate) is signed by its predecessor
              and the head of the chain is a trust anchor, i.e., its authenticity is assumed.
              <list style="empty">
              <t>Common aliases include: certificate chain.</t>
          </list>
          </t>
        </list></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="icn-node" title="ICN Node related terms">
        <t><list>
          <t>ICN Interface: a generalization of the network interface that can represent a physical network
              interface (ethernet, wifi, bluetooth adapter, etc.), an overlay inter-node channel (IP/UDP tunnel, etc.), or
              an intra-node IPC channel to an application (unix socket, shared memory, intents, etc.).
              <list style="empty">
              <t>Common aliases include: face.</t>
          </list>
          </t>

          <t>ICN Consumer: an ICN entity
              that requests data packets by generating and sending out interest packets towards local (using intra-node
              interfaces) or remote (using inter-node interfaces) ICN Forwarders.
              <list style="empty">
              <t>Common aliases include: consumer, information consumer, data consumer, consumer of the content.</t>
          </list>
          </t>

          <t>ICN Producer: an ICN entity that creates data packets and makes them available for retrieval.
              <list style="empty">
              <t>Common aliases include: producer, publisher, information publisher, data publisher, data producer.</t>
          </list>
          </t>

          <t>ICN Forwarder: an ICN entity that implements stateful forwarding.
              <list style="empty">
                  <t>Common aliases include: ICN router.</t>
             </list>
          </t>

          <t>Data Mule: an ICN entity that carries an interest or data packet before forwarding it to next ICN entity.</t>
        </list></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="stateful-forwarding" title="Stateful forwarding plane related terms">
        <t><list>
          <t>Stateful forwarding: a forwarding process that records incoming interest packets in the PIT and
              uses the recorded information to forward the retrieved data packets back to the consumer(s). The
              recorded information can also be used to measure data plane performance, e.g., to adjust interest
              forwarding strategy decisions.
              <list style="empty">
              <t>Common aliases include: ICN Data plane, ICN Forwarding.</t>
                </list>
          </t>

          <t>Name-based routing: a process of forwarding interest packets using the names
              in interests to guide the forwarding process</t>

          <t>ICN Pending Interest Table (PIT): a database that records received and not yet satisfied
              interests with the interfaces from where they were received. The PIT can also store
              interfaces to where Interests were forwarded, and information to assess data plane
              performance. Interests for the same data are aggregated into a single PIT entry.</t>

          <t>ICN Routing plane: an ICN protocol or a set of ICN protocols to exchange information about data packet availability.</t>

          <t>Satisfying an Interest: a process of forwarding the incoming data packet to the incoming interface(s) recorded in the corresponding PIT entry (entries) and removing the PIT entry (entries).</t>

          <t>Interest forwarding strategy: a module of the ICN stateful forwarding
              (ICN data) plane that implements a decision on where/how to forward the incoming interest packet. The
              forwarding strategy can take input from ICN Forwarding Information Base (FIB), measured data plane
              performance parameters, and/or use other mechanisms to make the decision.
              <list style="empty">
              <t>Common aliases include: forwarding strategy.</t>
          </list>
          </t>

          <t>Interest match in FIB (longest prefix match): a process of finding a FIB entry with the longest name (in terms of name components) that is a prefix of the specified name.</t>

          <t>Interest match in PIT (exact match): a process of finding a PIT entry that stores the same as specified interest (including interest restrictions, if any).</t>

          <t>Data match in PIT (all match): a process of finding (a set of) PIT entries that can be satisfied with the specified data packet.</t>

          <t>Interest match in CS (any match): a process of finding an entry in router’s content store that can satisfy the specified interest.</t>

          <t>Interest aggregation: a process of combining multiple
              interest packets for the same data into a single PIT entry.
              <list style="empty">
              <t>Common aliases include: interest suppression, interest collapsing.</t>
          </list>
          </t>

          <t>ICN Forwarding Information Base (FIB): a database that, for a set of prefixes, records a list of interfaces that can be used to retrieve data packets with names under the corresponding prefixes. The list of interfaces for each prefix can be ranked, and prefix/interfaces mapping , and interfaces can be associated with the additional information to facilitate forwarding strategy decisions.</t>

          <t>ICN Routing Information Base (RIB): a database that records a set of prefix-interface mappings that represent a candidate interface through which a data packet with the specified prefix can be retrieved. RIB can be used to populate FIB.</t>

          <t>Interest Nack: a packet that contains the interest packet and optional annotation,
              which is sent by the router to the interface(s) the Interest was received from. Interest Nack is used to inform downstream
              ICN nodes about inability to forward the included interest packet. The annotation can describe the reason.
              <list style="empty">
              <t>Common aliases include: network NACK, interest return.</t>
          </list>
          </t>

          <t>Upstream forwarding: forwarding packets in the direction of interests (i.e., interests are forwarded upstream): consumer, router, router, …, producer.</t>

          <t>Downstream forwarding: forwarding packets in the direction opposite of interest forwarding (i.e., data and interest nacks are forwarded downstream): producer, router, …, consumer(s).</t>

          <t>In-network storage: a process of storing a data packet within the network (in routers opportunistic on-path caches, in dedicated on/off path caches, and managed in-network storage systems), so it can satisfy an incoming interest for this data packet. The in-network storages can optionally advertise the stored data packets in the routing plane.</t>

          <t>Opportunistic caching (or on-path in-network caching or just caching): a process of temporarily storing a forwarded data packet in the router’s memory (RAM or disk), so it can be used to satisfy future interests for the same data, if any.</t>

          <t>Managed caching (or off-path in-network storage): a process of temporarily, permanently, or scheduled storing of a selected (set of) data packet(s).</t>

          <t>Content Store (CS): a database on an ICN router that provides opportunistic caching.</t>

          <t>Managed in-network storage (repository, repo): an entity acting as an ICN producer that implements managed caching.</t>

          <!--<t>Off-path caching:</t>
        <t></t>-->

          <!--<t>On-path caching:</t>
        <t></t>-->

          <!--<t>Cache poisoning</t>-->

          <!--<t>Name mapping resolution (same as name resolution, name mapping):</t>
        <t></t>-->
          <!-- AA: this seem to be not the right place. This implies a routing scalability solution that uses name mapping. May be we have a dedicated section on that -->
        </list></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="specific-solutions" title="Specific solution related terms">
          <t><list>
            <t>Route-By-Name Routing (RBNR)</t>
            <t>Lookup-By-Name Routing (LBNR)</t>
            <t>Bread-crumbs routing</t>
            <t>Replication-by-name</t>
            <t>Routing Locator Signing</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="uncategorized" title="Uncategorized terms">
        <t><list>
        <t>Content based</t>
        <t>ICN API</t>
        <t>Information Centric Delay Tolerant Network</t>
        <t>Located-Named-Data</t>
        <t>Sessionless</t>
        </list></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="semantics-and-usage" title="Semantics and Usage">

      <t>The terminology described above is the manifestation of
      intended semantics of NDN and CCNx operations (what do we expect
      the network to do?). In this section we summarize the most
      commonly proposed use cases and interpretations.</t>

      <section title="Data Transfer">
        <t>The networking view of NDN and CCNx is that the request/reply
        protocol implements a basic, unreliable data transfer service
        for single, named packets.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Data Transport">
        <t>Data transfer can be turned into a data transport service for
        application-level objects by additional logic. This transport logic
        must understand and constructs the series of names needed to
        reassemble the segmented object. Various flavors of transport
        can be envisaged (reliable, streaming, mailbox, etc)</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Lookup Service">
        <t>A more distributed systems view of the basic request/reply protocol
        is that NDN and CCNx provide a distributed lookup service:
        Given a key value (=name), the service will return the corresponding
        value.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Database Access">
        <t>The lookup service turns into a database access protocol by
        ... namespace design ... prefix standing for a collection ... The
        DB query expression must be encoded as a name.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Remote Procedure Call">
        <t>More generally, ... parameters in the interest ... used e.g.
        as command channel for remote control of neighbor routers.</t>
      </section>

    </section>

  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Informational References">
      <reference anchor="RFC7476"
                 target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc7476">
        <front>
          <title>Information-Centric Networking: Baseline Scenarios</title>

          <author fullname="K. Pentikousis" initials="K." role="editor"
                  surname="Pentikousis">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="B. Ohlman" initials="B." surname="Ohlman">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="D. Corujo" initials="D." surname="Corujo">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="G. Boggia" initials="G." surname="Boggia">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="G. Tyson" initials="G." surname="Tyson">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="E. Davies" initials="E." surname="Davies">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="A. Molinaro" initials="A." surname="Molinaro">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="S. Eum" initials="S." surname="Eum">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date month="March" year="2016"/>

          <abstract>
            <t>This document aims at establishing a common understanding about
            a set of scenarios that can be used as a base for the evaluation
            of different information-centric networking (ICN) approaches so
            that they can be tested and compared against each other while
            showcasing their own advantages. Towards this end, we review the
            ICN literature and document scenarios which have been considered
            in previous performance evaluation studies. We discuss a variety
            of aspects that an ICN solution can address. This includes general
            aspects, such as, network efficiency, reduced complexity,
            increased scalability and reliability, mobility support, multicast
            and caching performance, real-time communication efficiency,
            energy consumption frugality, and disruption and delay tolerance.
            We detail ICN-specific aspects as well, such as information
            security and trust, persistence, availability, provenance, and
            location independence.</t>

            <t>This document is a product of the IRTF Information-Centric
            Networking Research Group (ICNRG).</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="7476"/>

        <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC7476"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="I-D.irtf-icnrg-challenges">
        <front>
          <title>ICN Research Challenges</title>
          <author initials="D" surname="Kutscher" fullname="Dirk Kutscher">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="S" surname="Eum" fullname="Suyong Eum">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="K" surname="Pentikousis" fullname="Kostas Pentikousis">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="I" surname="Psaras" fullname="Ioannis Psaras">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="D" surname="Corujo" fullname="Daniel Corujo">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="D" surname="Saucez" fullname="Damien Saucez">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="T" surname="Schmidt" fullname="Thomas C. Schmidt">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="M" surname="Waehlisch" fullname="Matthias Waehlisch">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <date month="March" day="19" year="2016"/>
          <abstract>
            <t>
              This memo describes research challenges for Information-Centric Networking (ICN), an approach to evolve the Internet infrastructure to directly support information distribution by introducing uniquely named data as a core Internet principle. Data becomes independent from location, application, storage, and means of transportation, enabling or enhancing a number of desirable features, such as security, user-mobility, multicast and in-network caching. Mechanisms for realizing these benefits is subject of on-going research in the IRTF and elsewhere. This document describes current research challenges in ICN, including naming, security, routing, system scalability, mobility management, wireless networking, transport services, in-network caching, and network management. This document is a product of the IRTF Information-Centric Networking Research Group (ICNRG).
            </t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-irtf-icnrg-challenges-06"/>
        <format type="TXT" target="http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-irtf-icnrg-challenges-06.txt"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="I-D.irtf-icnrg-evaluation-methodology">
        <front>
          <title>
            Information-centric Networking: Evaluation and Security Considerations
          </title>
          <author initials="K" surname="Pentikousis" fullname="Kostas Pentikousis">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="B" surname="Ohlman" fullname="Borje Ohlman">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="E" surname="Davies" fullname="Elwyn B. Davies">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="S" surname="Spirou" fullname="Spiros Spirou">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="G" surname="Boggia" fullname="Gennaro Boggia">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <date month="April" day="12" year="2016"/>
          <abstract>
            <t>
              This document presents a number of considerations regarding evaluating Information-centric Networking (ICN) and sheds some light on the impact of ICN on network security. It also surveys the evaluation tools currently available to researchers in the ICN area and provides suggestions regarding methodology and metrics.
            </t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-irtf-icnrg-evaluation-methodology-05"/>
        <format type="TXT" target="http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-irtf-icnrg-evaluation-methodology-05.txt"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="I-D.irtf-icnrg-videostreaming">
        <front>
          <title>Adaptive Video Streaming over ICN</title>
          <author initials="c" surname="cedric.westphal@huawei.com" fullname="cedric.westphal@huawei.com">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="S" surname="Lederer" fullname="Stefan Lederer">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="C" surname="Mueller" fullname="Christopher Mueller">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="A" surname="Detti" fullname="Andrea Detti">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="D" surname="Corujo" fullname="Daniel Corujo">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="J" surname="Wang" fullname="Jianping Wang">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="M" surname="Montpetit" fullname="Marie-Jose Montpetit">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="N" surname="Murray" fullname="Niall Murray">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="C" surname="Timmerer" fullname="Christian Timmerer">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="D" surname="Posch" fullname="Daniel Posch">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="a" surname="aytav.azgin" fullname="aytav.azgin">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="S" surname="(Will)" fullname="Shucheng LIU (Will)">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <date month="April" day="28" year="2016"/>
          <abstract>
            <t>
              This document considers the consequences of moving the underlying network architecture from the current Internet to an Information- Centric Network (ICN) architecture on video distribution. As most of the traffic in future networks is expected to be video, we consider how to modify the existing video streaming mechanisms. Several important topics related to video distribution over ICN are presented, covering a wide range of scenarios: we look at how to evolve DASH to work over ICN, and leverage the recent ISO/IEC Moving Picture Experts Group (MPEG) Dynamic Adaptive Streaming over HTTP (DASH) standard; we consider layered encoding over ICN; Peer-to-Peer (P2P) mechanisms introduce distinct requirements for video and we look at how to adapt PPSP for ICN; Internet Protocol Television (IPTV) adds delay constraints, and this will create more stringent requirements over ICN as well. As part of the discussion on video, we discuss Digital Rights Management (DRM) in ICN. Finally, in addition to considering how existing mechanisms would be impacted by ICN, this document lists some research issues to design ICN specific video streaming mechanisms.
            </t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-irtf-icnrg-videostreaming-08"/>
        <format type="TXT" target="http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-irtf-icnrg-videostreaming-08.txt"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="I-D.irtf-icnrg-ccnxmessages">
        <front>
          <title>CCNx Messages in TLV Format</title>
          <author initials="m" surname="marc.mosko@parc.com" fullname="marc.mosko@parc.com">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="I" surname="Solis" fullname="Ignacio Solis">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="c" surname="cwood@parc.com" fullname="cwood@parc.com">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <date month="June" day="28" year="2016"/>
          <abstract>
            <t>
              This document specifies the encoding of CCNx messages using a TLV Packet specification. CCNx messages follow the CCNx Semantics specification. This document defines the TLV types used by each message element and the encoding of each value.
            </t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-irtf-icnrg-ccnxmessages-03"/>
        <format type="TXT" target="http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-irtf-icnrg-ccnxmessages-03.txt"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="I-D.irtf-icnrg-ccnxsemantics">
        <front>
          <title>CCNx Semantics</title>
          <author initials="m" surname="marc.mosko@parc.com" fullname="marc.mosko@parc.com">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="I" surname="Solis" fullname="Ignacio Solis">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="c" surname="cwood@parc.com" fullname="cwood@parc.com">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <date month="June" day="28" year="2016"/>
          <abstract>
            <t>
              This document describes the core concepts of the CCNx architecture and presents a minimum network protocol based on two messages: Interests and Content Objects. It specifies the set of mandatory and optional fields within those messages and describes their behavior and interpretation. This architecture and protocol specification is independent of a specific wire encoding. The protocol also uses a Control message called an InterestReturn, whereby one system can return an Interest message to the previous hop due to an error condition. This indicates to the previous hop that the current system will not respond to the Interest.
            </t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-irtf-icnrg-ccnxsemantics-03"/>
        <format type="TXT" target="http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-irtf-icnrg-ccnxsemantics-03.txt"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="I-D.irtf-icnrg-disaster">
        <front>
          <title>Using ICN in disaster scenarios</title>
          <author initials="J" surname="Seedorf" fullname="Jan Seedorf">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="M" surname="Arumaithurai" fullname="Mayutan Arumaithurai">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="A" surname="Tagami" fullname="Atsushi Tagami">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="K" surname="Ramakrishnan" fullname="K. Ramakrishnan">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="N" surname="Blefari-Melazzi" fullname="Nicola Blefari-Melazzi">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <date month="February" day="18" year="2016"/>
          <abstract>
            <t>
              Information Centric Networking (ICN) is a new paradigm where the network provides users with named content, instead of communication channels between hosts. This document outlines some research directions for Information Centric Networking with respect to applying ICN approaches for coping with natural or human-generated, large-scale disasters.
            </t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-irtf-icnrg-disaster-00"/>
        <format type="TXT" target="http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-irtf-icnrg-disaster-00.txt"/>
      </reference>
    </references>

    <section anchor="acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgments">
      <t>Mark Mosco, ...</t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
